Finding Aid for Washtenaw Intermediate School District records, 1834-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Washtenaw Intermediate School District records 1834-1966
Washtenaw Intermediate School District.
1 portfolios
21 oversize volumes
1 linear feet
85487 Bi 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The first accession of district records came to the library in 1977. Additional records were received in 2012. (Donor no. 6011 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The ancestor of the intermediate school district is the Office of County School Commissioner, which was established as an elective position by the Michigan legislature in 1867. The commissioner's major responsibility was to the rural township (nongraded) schools where he/she certified teachers, inspected the schools, supervised the curriculum, and advised township supervisors about needed improvements. The commissioner also filed all required state reports.
In 1935, the Michigan legislature authorized the option for elected county boards of education to appoint a county superintendent of schools, which was implemented in Washtenaw County in 1947. The responsibility to care for the rural primary districts was similar, but the county school superintendent was also placed at the center of the state's encouragement to reduce the number of primary districts in Michigan, consolidating them into K-12 units.
In the early 1960s, with most of the state's primary districts consolidated or in the process of consolidating, the legislature, through Public Act 190 of 1962, abolished the county school district and established the intermediate school district. In place of the emphasis on supervising primary districts, the intermediate school district assumed a central role in providing cooperative, coordinated educational services among many school districts in the name of economy and efficiency. The smaller counties were encouraged to consolidate with larger counties.
The records of the Washtenaw Intermediate School District predate the formal establishment of the District in 1962. Most probably, these materials were transferred from individuals concerned with the history of education and schools in Washtenaw County or from other previous county units responsible for the schools. The records have been arranged into four series: Nineteenth Century records; Manuscript school histories; Annual Statistical Reports; and Maps. The Annual Statistical Reports were for the Washtenaw County Township Clerk. These volumes, dating from school year 1902/03 to 1924/25, provide detailed information about the schools in the townships of the county. Included is the name of child, name of parent or guardian, number of children by sex, attendance records, names of teachers, and budget and salary information.
Subjects:
Dexter (Mich.: Township); Education--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Washtenaw County (Mich.). Board of School Inspectors.; Webster (Mich.); Ypsilanti (Mich.: Township)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Business enterprises--Michigan--Whitmore Lake.; Children--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Classrooms--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Drawings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Whitmore Lake.; Farms--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Rural schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Streets--Michigan--Whitmore Lake.; Teachers--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Schools.; Washtenaw Intermediate School District.; Whitmore Lake (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Whitmore Lake (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Whitmore Lake (Mich.)--Streets.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Nineteenth century records
  - Clerk's book 1834-1865 of the Webster Township school (Box 1)
  - Clerk's book circa 1837-1856, of Ypsilanti School District no. 2 (Box 1)
  - Clerk's book 1854-1934 of Dexter School District no. 7 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1881-1891 of the Washtenaw County Board of School Inspectors (Box 1)
- Manuscript school histories
  (include drawings and photographs)
  - Ann Arbor Township (Box 1)
  - Bridgewater (Box 1)
  - Dexter (Box 1)
  - Freedom (Box 1)
  - Lima (Box 1)
  - Lodi (Box 1)
  - Lyndon (Box 1)
  - Manchester (Box 1)
  - Northfield (Box 1)
  - Pittsfield (Box 1)
  - Salem (Box 1)
  - Saline (Box 1)
  - Scio (Box 1)
  - Sharon (Box 1)
  - Superior, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Sylvan (Box 1)
  - Webster (Box 1)
  - York (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti (Box 1)
  - General materials: history of Washtenaw County and its schools, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County schools newsletter 1945-1956, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- Annual statistical reports
  - 1902/03-1905/06 Ann Arbor-Northfield (Volume 1)
  - 1902/03-1905/06 Pittsfield-Ypsilanti (Volume 2)
  - 1906/07-1907/08 (Volume 3)
  - 1908-1909 (Volume 4)
  - 1909-1910 (Volume 5)
  - 1910-1911 (Volume 6)
  - 1911-1912 (Volume 7)
  - 1912-1913 (Volume 8)
  - 1913-1914 (Volume 9)
  - 1914-1915 (Volume 10)
  - 1915-1916 (Volume 11)
  - 1916-1917 (Volume 12)
  - 1917-1918 (Volume 13)
  - 1918-1919 (Volume 14)
  - 1919-1920 (Volume 15)
  - 1920-1921 (Volume 16)
  - 1921-1922 (Volume 17)
  - 1922-1923 (Volume 18)
  - 1923-1924 (Volume 19)
  - 1924-1925 (Volume 20)
- Maps
  - Washtenaw County atlas indicating school district boundaries and changes 1950s, 1 portfolios; 1 volumes (Volume 21)